Capital Area School Development Association; Records apap065
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Capital Area School Development Association (CASDA) Records
1949-1991
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Capital Area School Development Association
apap065
5 cubic ft.
CASDA is cooperative organization among public and private schools and the University at Albany's School of Education to facilitate programs for school employees.
Administrative History
The Capital Area School Development Association (CASDA) is a cooperative organization among public and private schools and the University at Albany's School of Education. Through programming, CASDA provides professional development for administrators, teachers, and school support staff. It is a voluntary self-governed association managed by an executive committee and chief school administrators. Its purpose is to facilitate programs for school employees. Finance is acquired through membership and the University.
CASDA was first suggested by a group of Schoharie County principals and school officials. Representatives from Schoharie and other schools met periodically in Albany, New York with faculty at the New York State College for Teachers to discuss changes in education and school affairs. The group aimed to network the college with public school teachers and administrators to introduce new philosophies, curriculum, and ideas. The group first convened as CASDA on October 6, 1949, and formed a study council to examine educational needs. Frank W. Frederick, Ph.D., chose the name of the organization, and a ten-member executive committee was formed to manage the association's operations at Milne Hall on the college's campus. CASDA organized during a period when education and the school experience was rapidly changing as a result of post-war expansion. Teachers wanted more development and professional services, and administrators felt a need for research and field services. The college provided these services to village, rural and city school personnel. CASDA's main purpose at the time of its inception was to create a link between K-12 teachers and the college to advance all aspects of education. The State Teacher's Colleges at Albany and Oneonta provided professional seminars. During its first few years of operation, CASDA mostly provided in-service programs for its members or to employees of schools who paid an annual fee to the association. Some of the first programs included television and radio workshops (1954-1957). In 1949, eighteen school districts had joined and CASDA's budget was $2,000. By 1950, thirty-seven schools had joined and by 1968 fifty had joined. Membership cost $.10 per pupil per school and the budget was $33,400. By 1970, BOCES schools became CASDA members. Seventy-three schools from eleven counties belonged to CASDA by 1986.
The executive committee consisted of administrators from the State Teachers College and local school administrators. Between four and twelve staff members and researchers also served CASDA before the 1980s. The first executive director was Joe Leese, 1949-1952. Other executive directors include Don Denley, 1953-1967; Bernard Bryan, 1967-1970; Al Farnsworth, 1970-1976; and Greg Benson, who took office in 1976. CASDA received federal funding for "Project B" in 1964 to study education in the region. In 1967, CASDA moved to the New York State Education Building in Albany, and in 1971 the association was chartered by the State Education Department. CASDA continued to organize conferences and seminars, and continued to form study councils. The council researched salaries, employee insurance issues, school budgets, and the economics of building construction. New programs included computer education and library media seminars. CASDA held annual administrative meetings, and annual conferences for first-year teachers, executive secretaries and custodians.
In 1986, the CASDA board consisted of ten members. Four staff members ran day-to-day operations with graduate assistants to support staff. In 1991, CASDA studied the problems of area schools and served 125 school districts with continuing education seminars. CASDA organized conferences for educators, school board members, and administrative staff. In 2006, Gregory Aidala was executive director, and CASDA was considered the third largest educational association in the United States. It is located on the East Campus of the University at Albany, in Rensselaer, New York, and is a study council of the University at Albany's School of Education.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the history of the association's management, activities, and programs from 1949 to 1991. Records include administrative papers, meeting minutes, and operations files of CASDA, published reports and newsletters, and conference programs and materials. The bulk of the collection contains publications and published reports from 1950 to 1970. The collection includes administrative records, publications, and reports of CASDA. Materials were kept by Edwin P. Adkins, Ph.D., who served from 1953-1963 as chairman of education at the New York State College for Teachers, which is now the University at Albany's School of Education.
Included in the administrative files series are minutes, programs, and materials from the annual CASDA meeting, minutes and memos from the administrative and executive committee conferences, and materials from general and regional meetings. The administrative papers also contain a history of the association, constitution and by-laws, financial records (1950-1969) and annual reports (1955-1960). This series contains annual calendars of CASDA events (1951-1962). There are letters, memos, and bulletins from the executive director (1960-1979). The administrative files contain documents related to studies and surveys conducted by CASDA's study council. Council minutes, research materials, and documents include examinations on teacher salaries, health insurance and benefits, public school opinion polls, and teacher promotion policies. There are also materials on special studies such as the Citizens Action Program (1953-1955). Publications include Casdaids, the association's newsletter (1949-1986) and the one-page leaflet, CASDAGram (1961, 1971-1988).
The bulk of the administrative files have documents related to seminars and conferences organized by CASDA from 1950 to 1965. Seminar materials related to curriculum and teacher development include topics such as elementary, junior high, high school, higher education, and adult education. There are materials for gifted and exceptional children, language arts, library education, moral and spiritual education, mental health, and disabled students. There are several documents relating to the professional development of non-teacher school staff. These include materials on the annual custodial and secretaries conferences. There are documents on school business management, and materials from school board clinics (1953-1973) and school law conferences (1953-1991).
There are three cubic feet of reports which date from 1950 to 1986, with most from 1950 to 1965. The bulk of the reports and publications address issues related to school administration and management, such as salary studies, teacher improvement, school law, student dropouts, school policy, and information for school board members. There are numerous CASDA survey reports. There also are reports and booklets for teachers on topics such as reading, economics, independent learning, and language arts. There are also booklets for non-teacher school staff such as handbooks for custodians and secretaries.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Acquisition Information
The items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries, M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, from the University Library's Education Bibliographer, via the Curriculum Library, by Susan Smith, Ph.D., in the spring of 1972.
Related Materials
Related collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives include the records of the School of Education (UA-650) and the Office of the President (UA-000). Additional related material can be found in the subject guides for Education and University at Albany, SUNY Administrative Records.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Schenectady, New York; Education; Albany, New York; Schools -- New York (State) -- Albany; Schools -- New York (State) -- Schenectady; Schools -- New York (State) -- Troy; Schools -- New York (State) -- Saratoga Springs; School superintendents -- Training of -- New York (State); School management and organization -- New York (State); Capital Area School Development Association..; State University of New York at Albany. School of Education
- Administrative Files, 1949-1991; 1; 2 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of materials relating to the daily and administrative operations of CASDA and information on the association's programs and research. It also contains two publications produced by CASDA. Most of the administrative papers relate to programs and date from the 1950s and 1960s.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Administrative Files, 1950-1987; 1.1; 0.75 cubic ft.
    These records document activities of the executive committee and CASDA staff, and relate to annual meetings attended by CASDA staff and school members. Other items found in the series include budget and finance reports, meeting minutes and programs, CASDA surveys, constitution and by-laws, organizational charts, and mission and history. There are records from special committees and study groups. There are news clippings, and some press releases. There also are publications CASDA collected from the Capital Area School Board Institute (1959-1985).
    - Activity Report, Program, 1983-1984; 1985-1986; 1986-1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
    - Administrative Seminars and Meetings, Memos, Minutes, Announcements, 1952-1955 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
    - Administrative Seminars, Meetings, Memos, 1956-1985 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
    - Administrative History and Mission, ca. 1970-1984 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
    - Annual Meeting Programs, 1953-1983 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
    - Annual Report of Activities and Programs, 1955-1956; 1958-1960 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
    - Behavioral Change Committee, Behavioral Change Teaching, 1952-1955 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
    - Business Management and Accounting Programs, 1955-1984 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
    - Calendar of Activities, Programs, Meetings, 1951-1962 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
    - Capital Area School Board Institute Pamphlets, 1959-1985 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
    - Casdaids Editorial File, 1951-1957 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
    - Citizens Education Project, 1953-1955 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
    - Community Studies Project, 1952 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
    - Constitutions and By-laws, 1954-1979 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
    - Economics of School Building Construction, 1955 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
    - Evaluation Meeting, 1959 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 16)
    - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, Programs, 1950-1965 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 17)
    - Executive Director Bulletins, Memos, Letters, 1960-1979 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 18)
    - Financial Reports and Data, Budget Reports, 1955-1969 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 19)
    - General Meetings Bulletins, Programs, 1951-1968 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 20)
    - Guides for Committee Chairmen, ca. 1950s (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 21)
    - Guide Sheets for Seminar Attendees, ca. 1957 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 22)
    - Meeting Announcements, 1953-1971 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 23)
    - News Clippings, 1956 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 24)
    - Organization Chart, ca. 1957; 1960 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 25)
    - Press Releases and Public Relations, 1951; 1967 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 26)
    - Principals' Center Networking Directory, ca. 1980 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 27)
    - Professional Growth of School Staff Member, 1957 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 28)
    - Program Brochures, 1973-1984 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 29)
    - Promotion Policy for Canajoharie's Schools, 1954 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 30)
    - Public School Opinion Poll, 1954; 1955; 1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 31)
    - Publications, Order Form, 1955; 1973; 1975 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 32)
    - Regional Meeting Programs, 1953-1955 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 33)
    - Salary Studies and Reports, 1954-1971 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 34)
    - School Board Clinics, 1953-1973 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 35)
    - School Studies Council Information, 1949-1956 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 36)
    - Statistical and Financial Survey, 1984-1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 37)
    - SUNY Certification Requirements for Teaching Secondary School, 1960 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 38)
    - Survey Questionnaires, Blank, and Results, 1952-1977 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 39)
    - Tape Recordings at CASDA, 1953 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 40)
    - Time For Education Leadership Working File, 1951 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 41)
    - US Office of Education, Project B Contract, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 42)
  - Conference and Program Seminars, 1949-1991; 1.2; 0.75 cubic ft.
    The bulk of the subseries contain seminar programs and materials CASDA organized for teachers, school staff, and education administrators. The subseries contains seminar minutes, programs, handouts, and meeting agendas.
    - Adult Education, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 43)
    - Child Development Seminar, 1955-1956 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 44)
    - Children at Risk and Early Childhood Education, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 45)
    - Conference Programs and Meetings, Miscellaneous, 1955-1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 46)
    - Coping with Curriculum Change Conference, 1967 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 47)
    - Custodial Conference Programs and Announcements, 1951-1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 48)
    - Custodial Bulletins, 1954-1955 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 48)
    - Disability Education Programs, 1956-1957 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 49)
    - Educational Secretaries Conference Programs, Memos, 1954-1987; 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 50)
    - Educational Television and Radio Workshops, 1954-1957 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 51)
    - Elementary Education Programs, 1951-1965 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 52)
    - First Year Teacher Study and Conference, 1951-1960 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 53)
    - Gifted and Exceptional Children Programs, 1955-1981 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 54)
    - Grouping in Classrooms, 1954 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
    - High School Education Programs, 1953-1987 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
    - Higher Education Programs and Information, 1952-1957 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
    - Independent Learning Program, 1953-1956 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
    - Junior High School Study and Programs, 1953-1968 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
    - Language Arts Study and Programs, 1956-1957; 1962 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
    - Leadership Conference, 1952; 1954 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
    - Library Conferences, 1954; 1986; 1987 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
    - Mental Health in Schools First Annual Conference on the Promotion of Learning and Adjustment in Schools, Program, 1986 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
    - Moral and Spiritual Education Program, 1954 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
    - Museum Education Workshop, 1960 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
    - National Study Council, Conference, 1957 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
    - Physical Education Program, 1955 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
    - Pupil Progress and Reporting, 1954-1955 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
    - Public Education: A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum, 1986 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
    - Reading Conferences and Workshops, 1973-1983 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 16)
    - Secondary Education Programs, 1957-1984 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 17)
    - School Law Conference, 1953; 1986-1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 18)
    - School Law Conference, 1989; 1991 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 19)
    - School Lunch Conference, Program, 1986 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 20)
    - Special Education Conference, 1973-1983 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 21)
    - Student Council, Student Government, 1954-1955 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 22)
    - Teacher Empowerment New Rule for Professionals, 1987 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 23)
    - Teacher Evaluations and Professional Growth Program, 1957 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 24)
    - Transportation Supervisors Meeting, 1977; 1978 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 25)
    - Truth About our Public Schools, 1954 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 26)
    - Understanding Public Opinion, 1955 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 27)
  - Casdaids and CASDAGram Newsletters, 1949-1986; 1.3; 0.5 cubic ft.
    This contains the newsletter Casdaids published by CASDA and distributed to members. The collection holds issues for the period 1949-1986. CASDAGram is a leaflet that announced programs and meetings organized by CASDA.
    - CASDAGram, 1961; 1971-1976 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 28)
    - CASDAGram, 1977-1979 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 29)
    - CASDAGram, 1979-1982 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 30)
    - CASDAGram, 1983-1984 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 31)
    - CASDAGram, 1984-1985 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 32)
    - CASDAGram, 1985-1987 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 33)
    - CASDAGram, 1987-1988 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 34)
    - Casdaids, 1949-1951 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 35)
    - Casdaids, 1951 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 36)
    - Casdaids, 1952-1955 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 37)
    - Casdaids, 1956-1959 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 38)
    - Casdaids, 1959-1973 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 39)
    - Casdaids, 1973-1986 (Box 2 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 40)
- Reports and Publications, 1950-1994; 2; 3 cubic ft.
  This series consists of reports and booklets published by CASDA. The bulk of the reports were produced for school administrators and address school management, human resources, and business and legal issues. Many of the reports publish the findings of CASDA's study councils and surveys conducted by researchers. They document size, financial issues, and administration of CASDA schools. Other reports are handbooks for teachers and address curriculum, education philosophy, special programs, and teaching methods. There also are custodian handbooks and bibliographies for teachers.
  Arranged chronologically, then alphabetically.
  - Humanagement in CASDA Schools, 1950 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 1)
  - Humanagement in CASDA Schools, 1950 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 2)
  - The Improvement of Reading, CASDA, 1950 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 3)
  - Improving the Public's Understanding of Our Schools, 1950 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 4)
  - Individual and Group Reading, 1950 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 5)
  - Integrating the Elementary Curriculum, 1950 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 6)
  - Promising Practices, 1950 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 7)
  - Twelfth Grade Electives in English, 1950 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 8)
  - Administrative Leadership in Community Planning for Education, 1951 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 9)
  - Fare for the Reluctant Reader, 1951 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 10)
  - Helping the First Year Teacher, 1951 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 11)
  - Philadelphia Suburban School Study Council, 1951-1952 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 12)
  - Wilmington Delaware Public Schools, Undated (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 12)
  - Role of General Mathematics in the Drop-Out Problem, 1951 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 13)
  - Report of First Annual Custodial Conference at State College for Teachers, 1951 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 14)
  - Sound Financial Planning for Modern Education, 1951 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 15)
  - Suggested Practices for Science Teachers, 1951 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 16)
  - Time for Educational Leadership, 1951 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 17)
  - Understanding and Teaching the Slow Learner, A Bibliography, ca. 1951 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 18)
  - Administrative Seminar Project, 1952 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 19)
  - Administrator and Group Dynamics, 1952 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 20)
  - Facts Should Make a Difference When Dealing With Complaints and Attacks on Certain Aspects of American Education, 1952 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 21)
  - Fare for the Reluctant Reader, ca. 1952 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 22)
  - More Help for the Beginning Teacher, 1952 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 23)
  - Problems of School Boards and Administrators, 1952 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 24)
  - Problems of Teacher Compensation, 1952 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 25)
  - Problems of Teacher Selection and Improvement, 1952 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 26)
  - Report and Recommendations on the Administration, Office Management and Business Procedures of Scotia Glenville Central Schools, 1952 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 27)
  - Report of Second Annual Conference, 1952 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 28)
  - Survey! Salaries Policies and Incomes of CASDA Schools, 1952-1953 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 29)
  - Award Programs Delaware Schools, 1953 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 30)
  - Better Schools Through Better Maintenance, 1953 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 31)
  - Elementary School Journal, 1953 May (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 32)
  - New School Board Member, 1953 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 33)
  - Survey of the School Building Needs of the Arnold School District, Amsterdam, 1953 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 34)
  - Education for Better Use of our Resources, 1954 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 35)
  - Practical Programs for Moral and Spiritual Education, 1954 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 36)
  - Salary Policies and Finance Data, 1954-1955 (Box 1 (2-Reports and Publications), Folder 37)